Everybody in our society's life is touched by cancer --
كل شخص في حياة مجتمعنا يتأثر بالسرطان --
if not personally,
إذا لم يكن بصفة شخصية،
then through a loved one, a family member,
فعن طريق شخص نحبّه أو فرد من العائلة
colleague, friend.
أو زميل أو صديق.
And once our lives are touched by cancer,
وعندما تتأثر حيواتنا بالسرطان
we quickly learn
سرعان ما نتعلم
that there are basically
أن هناك في الأساس
three weapons, or three tools, that are available
ثلاثة أسلحة أو ثلاثة أدوات متوفرة
to fight the disease:
لمقاومة المرض:
surgery, radiation and chemotherapy.
الجراحة والأشعة والعلاج الكيميائي.
And once we get involved
و لحظة انغماسنا
in the therapeutic decisions,
في القرارات العلاجية
again either personally
ومرة أخرى سواء بصفة شخصية
or with our loved ones and family members,
أو عن طريق الأشخاص الذين نحبهم أو أفراد العائلة،
we also very quickly learn
كذلك سريعا جدا ما نعلم
the benefits, the trade-offs and the limitations
المحاسن والأفضليات وحدود
of these tools.
هذه الأدوات.
I'm very thankful to Jay and to Mark
أنا شاكر جدا لجاي ومارك
and the TEDMED team
وفريق TEDMED
for inviting me today
لاستضافتهم اليوم لي
to describe a fourth tool, a new tool,
لأصف أداة رابعة، أداة جديدة
that we call Tumor Treating Fields.
نسميها الحقول المعالجة للورم.
Tumor Treating Fields
الحقول المعالجة للورم
were invented by Dr. Yoram Palti,
اُخترعت من قبل د. يورام بالتاي،
professor emeritus at the Technion in Israel.
وهو أستاذ متميز في معهد التقنية في إسرائيل.
And they use low-intensity
ويستعملون حقولا كهربائية
electric fields
ذات شدّة ضعيفة
to fight cancer.
لمقاومة السرطان.
To understand how Tumor Treating Fields work,
لكي نفهم كيف تعمل الحقول المعالجة للورم،
we first need to understand
نحتاج أولا لفهم
what are electric fields.
ما هي الحقول الكهربائية.
Let me first address
دعوني أتطرّق أولا
a few popular misconceptions.
لبعض المفاهيم الخاطئة الشائعة.
First of all, electric fields
في المقام الأول، الحقول الكهربائية
are not an electric current
ليست تيارا كهربائيا
that is coursing through the tissue.
يمرّ عبر النسيج.
Electric fields
الحقول الكهربائية
are not ionizing radiation,
ليست إشعاعات تحتوي على أيونات
like X-rays or proton beams,
مثل اشعاعات إكس أو اشعاعات البروتون،
that bombard tissue
التي تضرب النسيج
to disrupt DNA.
لتحدث خللا في الحمض الريبي النووي.
And electric fields
والحقول الكهربائية
are not magnetism.
لا تعني المغناطيسية.
What electric fields are
فيما تتمثل الحقول الكهربائية
are a field of forces.
إنها حقل من القوى.
And these forces
وهذه القوى
act on, attract, bodies
تجذب وتؤثر في الأجسام
that have an electrical charge.
التي لديها شحنة كهربائية.
The best way to visualize an electric field
الطريقة الفضلى لتصوّر حقل كهربائي
is to think of gravity.
تتمثل في التفكير في الجاذبية.
Gravity is also a field of forces
الجاذبية هي أيضا حقل من القوى
that act on masses.
تؤثر على الكتل.
We can all picture astronauts in space.
كلنا نستطيع تصوّر الرواد في الفضاء.
They float freely in three dimensions
يطوفون بحرية في أبعاد ثلاثة
without any forces acting on them.
دون أي قوى تؤثر فيهم.
But as that space shuttle
لكن عندما يقوم مكوك الفضاء
returns to Earth,
بالرجوع للأرض،
and as the astronauts enter the Earth's gravitational field,
وعندما يدخل رواد الفضاء لحقل جاذبية الأرض،
they begin to see the effects of gravity.
يبدأون بملاحظة تأثيرات الجاذبية.
They begin to be attracted towards Earth.
يبدأون بالانجذاب نحو الأرض.
And as they land,
وعندما يطأون الأرض،
they're fully aligned in the gravitational field.
فإنهم يخضعون تماما لحقل الجاذبية.
We're, of course, all stuck in the Earth's gravitational field right now.
طبعا جميعنا عالقون في حقل جاذبية الأرض في هذه اللحظة.
That's why you're all in your chairs.
لذلك كلكم لازلتم في كراسيكم.
And that's why we have to use our muscle energy
ولذلك يجب ان نستخدم طاقتنا العضلية
to stand up, to walk around
لنقف ونتجول
and to lift things.
ونرفع الأشياء.
In cancer,
بالنسبة للسرطان،
cells rapidly divide
تنقسم الخلايا بسرعة
and lead to uncontrolled tumor growth.
وتؤدّي لانتشار ورم.
We can think of a cell
نستطيع التفكير في خلية
from an electrical perspective
من زاوية علم الكهرباء
as if it's a mini space station.
كأنها محطة فضاء مصغّرة.
And in that space station
وفي محطة الفضاء تلك
we have the genetic material, the chromosomes,
لدينا المادة الوراثية، الكروموسومات (الصبغيات)
within a nucleus.
التي توجد داخل نواة.
And out in the cytoplasmic soup
وفي الخارج داخل الحساء الهيولي (السيتوبلازمي)
we have special proteins
لدينا بروتينات خاصة
that are required for cell division
لازمة لانقسام الخلايا
that float freely in this soup
التي تطوف بحرية في هذا الحساء
in three dimensions.
في ثلاثة أبعاد.
Importantly, those special proteins
من المهم الإشارة إلى أن تلك البروتينات الخاصة
are among the most highly charged objects
هي ضمن أكثر الأجسام شحنا
in our body.
في أجسامنا.
As cell division begins
وعندما يبدأ انقسام الخلايا
the nucleus disintegrates,
تتآكل النواة
the chromosomes line up
تصطف الصبغيات
in the middle of the cell
في وسط الخلية
and those special proteins
وتلك البروتينات الخاصة
undergo a three-dimensional sequence
تخضع لتسلسل ثلاثي الأبعاد
whereby they attach
تلتحم فيه كل واحدة بالأخرى
and they literally click into place end-on-end
ويتسمرون في مكانهم من الطرف للطرف
to form chains.
ليكوّنوا سلاسل.
These chains
هذه السلاسل
then progress and attach
تتقدّم وتلتحم
to the genetic material
بالمادة الوراثية
and pull the genetic material
وتسحب المادة الوراثية
from one cell into two cells.
من خلية إلى خليتين.
And this is exactly how
وهذا تماما كيف
one cancer cell becomes two cancer cells,
خلية سرطان واحدة تصبح خليتي سرطان
two cancer cells become four cancer cells,
وخليتا سرطان تصبحان أربع خلايا سرطان
and we have ultimately
وفي النهاية لدينا
uncontrolled tumor growth.
انتشار ورم.
Tumor Treating Fields
الحقول المعالجة للورم
use externally placed transducers
تستعمل محولات طاقة موضوعة خارجيا
attached to a field generator
موصولة بموّلد حقل
to create an artificial electric field
لتخلق حقل كهربائي اصطناعي
on that space station.
في محطة الفضاء تلك.
And when that cellular space station
وعندما تكون محطة الفضاء الخلوية تلك
is within the electric field,
في مجال الحقل الكهربائي،
it acts on those highly charged proteins
تؤثّر على تلك البروتينات عالية الشحنة
and aligns them.
وتجمعهم في خط مستقيم.
And it prevents them from forming those chains,
وتمنعهم من تكوين تلك السلاسل.
those mitotic spindles,
وهذا الانقسام الفتيلي
that are necessary to pull the genetic material
الذي هو ضروري لسحب المادة الوراثية
into the daughter cells.
في الخلايا الوليدة.
What we see is that the cells will attempt to divide
ما نراه هو ان الخلايا ستحاول الانقسام
for several hours.
لعدّة ساعات
And they will either enter into
وسيدخلون إمّا في
this so-called cellular suicide,
هذا الذي يسمّى الانتحار الخلوي أي
programmed cell death,
الموت المبرمج للخلايا
or they will form unhealthy daughter cells
أو سيكوّنون خلايا وليدة غير صحية
and enter into apoptosis
ويدخلون في استماتة.
once they have divided.
عند انقسامهم.
And we can observe this.
ونستطيع أن نلحظ هذا.
What I'm going to show you next
ما سأعرضه عليكم لاحقا يتمثل في
are two in vitro experiments.
تجربتين داخل الأنبوب.
This is cultures, identical cultures,
هاتان عمليتا زرع متطابقتان
of cervical cancer cells.
لخلايا سرطان الرحم.
And we've stained these cultures
وخضّبنا هذان الزرعان
with a green florescent dye
بملوّن أخضر متألق
so that we can look at these proteins
كي نرى هذه البروتينات
that form these chains.
التي تؤلّف هذه السلاسل.
The first clip shows
يظهر مقطع الفيديو الأول
a normal cell division
انقسام خلوي معتاد
without the Tumor Treating Fields.
دون الحقول المعالجة للورم.
What we see
ما نراه
are, first of all, a very active culture,
يتمثل في، أولا زرع نشيط جدا
a lot of divisions,
وكثير من الانقسامات
and then very clear nuclei
ثم أنوية واضحة جدا
once the cells have separated.
عند انفصال الخلايا.
And we can see them dividing throughout.
ونستطيع رؤيتهم ينقسمون.
When we apply the fields --
عندما نضع الحقول --
again, in the identical time-scale
مرة أخرى في ميزان وقتي متطابق
to the identical culture --
و في زرع متطابق --
you're going to see something different.
سترون شيئا مختلفا.
The cells round up for division,
تتجمع الخلايا لتنقسم،
but they're very static in that position.
لكنها ثابتة جدا في ذلك الموقع.
We'll see two cells
سنرى خليتان
in the upper part of the screen
في الجزء العلوي من الشاشة
attempting to divide.
تحاولان الانقسام.
The one within the circle manages.
تنجح الخلية التي ضمن الدائرة.
But see how much of the protein
لكن أنظروا كم من البروتين
is still throughout the nucleus,
لازال ضمن النواة،
even in the dividing cell.
حتى في الخلية التي في طور الانقسام.
The one up there can't divide at all.
الخلية التي هناك لا تستطيع الانقسام إطلاقا.
And then this bubbling, this membrane bubbling,
وفوران الغشاء
is the hallmark
هو السمة المميزة
of apoptosis in this cell.
للاستماتة في هذه الخلية.
Formation of healthy mitotic spindles
تكون مغازل انقسام خلوي سليمة
is necessary for division
ضروري للانقسام
in all cell types.
في جميع أنواع الخلايا.
We've applied Tumor Treating Fields
طبقّنا الحقول المعالجة للورم
to over 20 different cancers in the lab,
على أكثر من 20 نوعا من السرطانات في المختبر
and we see this effect
ورأينا هذا التأثير
in all of them.
فيهم كلّهم.
Now importantly,
من المهم جدا الآن
these Tumor Treating Fields have no effect
ليس لدى هذه الحقول المعالجة للورم أي تأثير
on normal undividing cells.
على الخلايا العادية غير المنقسمة.
10 years ago,
منذ 10 سنوات،
Dr. Palti founded a company called Novocure
أسس د. بولتي شركة تُدعى نوفوكيور
to develop his discovery
ليطوّر اكتشافه
into a practical therapy for patients.
ليصبح علاجا عمليا للمرضى.
In that time, Novocure's developed two systems --
في ذلك الوقت، طوّرت نوفوكيور نظامين --
one system for cancers in the head
نظاما للسرطانات في الرأس
and another system for cancers in the trunk of the body.
ونظاما آخر للسرطانات في جذع الجسم.
The first cancer that we have focused on
السرطان الاول الذي ركّزنا عليه
is the deadly brain cancer, GBM.
هو سرطان الدماغ المميت، الورم الأرومي الدبقي.
GBM affects about 10,000 people
يصاب حوالي 10,000 شخص بالورم الأرومي الدبقي
in the U.S. each year.
في الولايات المتحدة كل عام.
It's a death sentence.
إنه حكم بالإعدام.
The expected five year survival
مدّة الخمس سنوات المتوقعة للعيش
is less than five percent.
أقل من خمسة بالمئة.
And the typical patient
والمريض العادي
with optimal therapy
الخاضع لعلاج جيد
survives just a little over a year,
يبقى حيا لأكثر بقليل من سنة
and only about seven months
ولسبعة أشهر فقط
from the time that the cancer is first treated
ابتداءا من وقت معالجة السرطان لأول مرة
and then comes back and starts growing again.
ثم يعود ويبدأ في النمو مجددا.
Novocure conducted
أجرت نوفوكيور
its first phase three randomized trial
في المرحلة الأولى ثلاث تجارب عشوائية
in patients with recurrent GBM.
على مرضى بالورم الأرومي الدبقي المتواتر.
So these are patients
إذن هؤلاء مرضى
who had received surgery,
خضعوا للجراحة
high dose radiation to the head
ولعلاج إشعاعي ذي جرعة عالية في الرأس
and first-line chemotherapy,
ولعلاج كيميائي من الدرجة الأولى
and that had failed and their tumors had grown back.
لكن ذلك فشل وعاودت أورامهم النمو.
We divided the patients into two groups.
قسّمنا المرضى لمجموعتين.
The first group received second-line chemotherapy,
تلقت المجموعة الأولى علاجا كيميائيا من الدرجة الثانية
which is expected to double the life expectancy,
والتي من المتوقع ان تضاعف أمل الحياة
versus no treatment at all.
مقارنة بعدم العلاج تماما.
And then the second group
وأمّا المجموعة الثانية
received only Tumor Treating Field therapy.
فقد تلقت علاجا بالحقل المعالج للورم.
What we saw in that trial
ما رأيناه في تلك التجربة
is that that the life expectancies of both groups --
هو أن أمل الحياة لكلا المجموعتين --
so the chemotherapy treated group
وهما المجموعة المعَالجة بالعلاج الكيميائي
and the Tumor Treating Field group --
ومجموعة الحقل المعالج للورم --
was the same.
كان نفسه.
But importantly,
لكن من المهم جدّا أن
the Tumor Treating Field group
مجموعة الحقل المعالج للورم
suffered none of the side effects
لم تعاني من أيّا من الأعراض الجانبية
typical of chemotherapy patients.
المميزة لمرضى العلاج الكيميائي.
They had no pain,
لم يكن لديهم أي آلام
suffered none of the infections.
ولم يشكوا أيا من الالتهابات.
They had no nausea, diarrhea,
لم يكن لديهم أي غثيان أو إسهال
constipation, fatigue
أو إمساك أو إجهاد
that would be expected.
متوقع.
Based on this trial,
بناءا على هذه التجربة،
in April of this year,
في أبريل من هذه السنة
the FDA approved Tumor Treating Fields
أقرّت إدارة الغذاء والدواء الحقول المعالجة للورم
for the treatment of patients
لعلاج مرضى
with recurrent GBM.
الورم الأرومي الدبقي المتواتر.
Importantly, it was the first time ever
من المهم جدا أنه للمرة الأولى على الإطلاق
that the FDA included
ضمّنت إدارة الغذاء والدواء
in their approval of an oncology treatment
في موافقتهم على علاج لورم
a quality of life claim.
زعما حول حياة مريحة.
So I'm going to show you now
لذلك ساُريكم الآن
one of the patients
أحد المرضى
from this trial.
من هذه التجربة.
Robert Dill-Bundi
روبرت ديل-بوندي
is a famous Swiss cycling champion.
وهو بطل سباقات دراجات سويسري مشهور.
He won the gold medal in Moscow
فاز بالميدالية الذهبية في موسكو
in the 4,000 meter pursuit.
في سباق تسارع الـ 4,000 متر.
And five years ago,
ومنذ خمس سنوات
Robert was diagnosed with GBM.
شُخّصت إصابة روبرت بالورم الأرومي الدبقي.
He received the standard treatments.
تلقّى العلاجات الاعتيادية.
He received surgery.
تلقّى الجراحة.
He received high dose radiation to the head.
تلقّى علاجا اشعاعيا عالي الجرعة في الرأس.
And he received first-line chemotherapy.
وتلقّى علاجا كيميائيا من الدرجة الأولى.
A year after this treatment --
بعد سنة من هذا العلاج --
in fact, this is his baseline MRI.
في الواقع، هذه صورة بالرنين المغناطيسي قبل العلاج الكيمياوي.
You can see that the black regions
يمكن أن تروا أن المناطق السوداء
in the upper right quadrant
في ربع الدائرة الأيمن العلوي
are the areas where he had surgery.
هي المناطق الخاضعة للجراحة.
And a year after that treatment,
وبعد سنة من ذلك العلاج،
his tumor grew back with a vengeance.
نما ورمه مجددا بصفة انتقامية.
That cloudy white mass that you see
ذلك التجمع الابيض السحابي الذي ترونه
is the recurrence of the tumor.
هو معاودة ظهور الورم.
At this point, he was told by his doctors
في هذه اللحظة أخبره أطباؤه
that he had about 3 months to live.
أنّ لديه حوالي 3 أشهر ليعيش.
He entered our trial.
دخل في تجربتنا.
And here we can see him getting the therapy.
وهنا يمكننا رؤيته يخضع للعلاج.
First of all, these electrodes are noninvasive.
أولا، هذه الإلكترودات غير باضعة.
They're attached to the skin
فقد اُلصقت بالجلد
in the area of the tumor.
في منطقة الورم.
Here you can see
يمكنكم هنا أن تروا
that a technician is placing them on there much like bandages.
أن فنيا يضعهم هناك مثل الضمادات إلى حد كبير.
The patients learn to do this themselves
يتعلم المرضى القيام بذلك بأنفسهم
And then the patients
ثم يمكن للمرضى
can undergo all the activities of their daily life.
القيام بكل نشاطات حياتهم اليومية.
There's none of the tiredness.
ليس هناك أي إجهاد.
There's none of what is called the "chemo head."
ليس هناك أي شيء من الذي يدُعى "الرأس الكيميائي"
There's no sensation.
ليس هناك أي إحساس.
It doesn't interfere
لا تتداخل
with computers or electrical equipment.
مع الحواسيب أو الأجهزة الكهربائية.
And the therapy is delivered continuously
ويقدَم العلاج بصفة مستمرة
at home,
في البيت
without having to go into the hospital
دون ضرورة الذهاب للمستشفى
either periodically or continually.
بصفة دورية أو مستمرة.
These are Robert's MRIs,
هذه صور الرنين المغناطيسي لروبرت
again, under only TTField treatment.
مرة أخرى، وهو يخضع للعلاج بالحقل المعالج للورم.
This is a therapy that takes time to work.
هذا علاج يتطلب وقتا ليعطي تأثيره.
It's a medical device;
إنه جهاز طبي
it works when it's on.
يعمل عندما يكون في وضع اشتغال.
But what we can see is, by month six,
لكن ما يمكننا رؤيته أنه مع الشهر السادس
the tumor has responded
استجاب الورم
and it's begun to melt away.
وبدأ في التلاشي.
It's still there.
لا زال موجودا هناك.
By month 12,
بداية من الشهر 12
we could argue whether
يمكننا أن نزعم
there's a little bit of material around the edges,
أن هناك قليلا من المادة حول الأطراف،
but it's essentially completely gone.
لكنه في الأساس ذهب تماما.
It's now five years
إنها الآن خمس سنوات
since Robert's diagnosis,
منذ تشخيص إصابة روبرت
and he's alive,
ولازال حيا
but importantly, he's healthy
لكن المهم أنه معافى
and he's at work.
ومنخرط في العمل.
I'm going to let him, in this very short clip,
سأدعه في مقطع الفيدو الصغير جدا هذا
describe his impressions of the therapy
يصف انطباعاته حول العلاج
in his own words.
بكلماته هو.
(Video) Robert Dill-Bundi: My quality of life,
(فيديو) روبرت ديل-بوندي: نوعية حياتي
I rate what I have today
اُقيّم ما لدي اليوم
a bit different than what most people would assume.
بطريقة مختلفة قليلا عما يعتبره معظم الناس.
I am the happiest, the happiest person in the world.
أنا أسعد، أسعد شخص في العالم.
And every single morning I appreciate life.
وفي كل صباح اُقدر قيمة الحياة.
Every night I fall asleep very well,
كل ليلة اخلد لنوم هانئ
and I am, I repeat,
وأنا، أكرر،
the happiest man in the world,
أسعد رجل في العالم
and I'm thankful I am alive.
وإنني ممتن لأنني على قيد الحياة.
BD: Novocure's also working on lung cancer
بيل دويل: اشتغلت أيضا نوفوكيور على سرطان الرئة
as the second target.
كالهدف الثاني.
We've run a phase two trial
قمنا بمرحلة ثانية من التجربة
in Switzerland
في سويسرا
on, again, recurrent patients --
مرة اُخرى على مرضى عاودهم المرض --
patients who have received standard therapy
مرضى خضعوا لعلاج اعتيادي
and whose cancer has come back.
وعاودهم السرطان.
I'm going to show you another clip
ساُريكم مقطع فيديو آخر
of a woman named Lydia.
لإمرأة تُدعى ليديا.
Lydia's a 66 year-old farmer
ليديا هي مزارعة في السادسة والستين من العمر
in Switzerland.
في سويسرا.
She was diagnosed with lung cancer
شُخصت بإصابتها بالسرطان
five years ago.
منذ خمس سنوات.
She underwent four different regimes of chemotherapy
خضعت لأربعة أنظمة تداوي مختلفة من العلاج الكيميائي
over two years,
خلال سنتين
none of which had an effect.
ليس لدى أيّا منهم أي تأثير.
Her cancer continued to grow.
استمر سرطانها في النمو.
Three years ago,
منذ ثلاث سنوات
she entered the Novocure lung cancer trial.
دخلت في تجربة نوفوكيور لسرطان الرئة.
You can see, in her case,
يمكنكم رؤية
she's wearing her transducer arrays,
هي مرتدية تشكيلات من محولات الطاقة
one of the front of her chest, one on the back,
واحد أمام صدرها وواحد في ظهرها
and then the second pair side-to-side over the liver.
ثم الزوج الثاني يمتد جنبا لجنب فوق الكبد.
You can see the Tumor Treating Field field generator,
يمكنكم رؤية موّلد حقل الحقل المعالج للورم،
but importantly you can also see that she is living her life.
لكن الأهم أنه يمكنكم أيضا أن تروا أنها تعيش حياتها.
She is managing her farm.
إنها تدير مزرعتها.
She's interacting with her kids and her grand kids.
إنها تتواصل مع أطفالها وأحفادها.
And when we talked to her,
وعندما تحدثنا إليها،
she said that when she was undergoing chemotherapy,
قالت أنها عندما خضعت للعلاج الكيميائي،
she had to go to the hospital every month for her infusions.
وجب عليها الذهاب للمستشفى كل شهر لأجل حقناتها.
Her whole family suffered
عانت كل عائلتها
as her side effect profile came and went.
عندما عانت من حالة متقلبة من الأضرار الجانبية.
Now she can run
يمكنها الآن أن تدير
all of the activities of her farm.
كل أنشطة مزرعتها.
It's only the beginning.
إنها مجرّد البداية.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
In the lab, we've observed tremendous synergies
في المختبر، لاحظنا تآزرا كبيرا
between chemotherapy and Tumor Treating Fields.
بين العلاج الكيميائي والحقول المعالجة للورم.
There's research underway now at Harvard Medical School
هناك بحث قيد الإجراء في كلية هارفارد للطب
to pick the optimum pairs
لانتقاء أفضل زوجين
to maximize that benefit.
لتعظيم المنفعة.
We also believe that Tumor Treating Fields will work with radiation
نعتقد أيضا أن الحقول المعالجة للورم ستتفاعل مع الأشعة
and interrupt the self-repair mechanisms that we have.
وستعيق آليات الترميم الذاتي التي لدينا.
There's now a new research project underway
هناك الآن مشروع بحث قيد الإجراء
at the Karolinska in Sweden
في كارولينسكا في السويد
to prove that hypothesis.
ليثبتوا تلك الفرضية.
We have more trials planned
لدينا المزيد من التجارب المبرمجة
for lung cancer,
حول سرطان الرئة
pancreatic cancer, ovarian cancer
وسرطان البنكرياس وسرطان المبيض
and breast cancer.
وسرطان الثدي.
And I firmly believe
واعتقد جازما
that in the next 10 years
أنه في السنوات العشر القادمة
Tumor Treating Fields
الحقول المعالجة للورم
will be a weapon available to doctors and patients
ستكون سلاحا متوفرا لدى للأطباء والمرضى
for all of these most-difficult-to-treat solid tumors.
لكل هذه الأورام الصلبة صعبة العلاج.
I'm also very hopeful
أنا أيضا كلّي أمل
that in the next decades,
أنه في العقود القادمة
we will make big strides
سنتقدم خطوات كبيرة
on reducing that death rate
في الحد من نسبة الموت تلك
that has been so challenging in this disease.
التي كانت عصية جدا في هذا المرض.
Thank you.
شكرا لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)